Guy Gabrielson Papers
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Guy Gabrielson Papers 1925-1967
nam_apap248
The Guy Gabrielson Papers contain materials that document the political career of Guy George Gabrielson from his start in New Jersey state politics through his years as Chairman of the Republican National Committee. Many of the materials document the 1952 U.S. Presidential election and Republican National Committee Convention which Gabrielson presided over as chairman.
Gabrielson, Guy George, 1891-1976
5.5 cubic ft. 1 Digital Files
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Syracuse University received the papers of Guy George Gabrielson in a series of acquisitions in 1965 and 1967 and subsequently transferred them to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2006.
Biographical Sketch
Guy George Gabrielson was born in Sioux Rapids, Iowa in May 1891. He received a bachelor of arts degree from the University of Iowa in 1914 and a law degree from Harvard University in 1917. From 1917-1919 he served as a private in the U.S. Army. His political career began in 1925 as a Republican member of the General Assembly of New Jersey from Essex County; in 1929 he became the General Assemblys Speaker of the House. He became the Executive Director of the New Jersey State Campaign in 1936 and its chairman in 1940. Gabrielson was a member of the Republican National Committee (RNC) from 1944-1952 and RNC Chairman from 1949-1952. In 1951 he was involved in a loan scandal that prompted Senator Richard Nixon to call for his removal as chairman. Gabrielson left the RNC in 1952 and returned to practicing law. He later became acting chief executive and president of the John Wood Company of New York and chairman of the Nichold Company of Delaware. Gabrielson died in May of 1976 in Point Pleasant, New Jersey, preceded in death by his wife Cora. The couple had two children.
Gabrielson is best known for his work as chairman of the RNC. In 1952 he opened the convention that nominated General Dwight D. Eisenhower for president. Gabrielson was a controversial figure at the convention; his support of Ohio Senator Robert Taft for the presidential nomination offended backers of Eisenhower who believed that Gabrielson was using his privileges as party chairman to promote the candidacy of Senator Taft.
This collection contains materials that document the political career of Guy George Gabrielson from his start in New Jersey state politics through his years as chairman of the Republican National Committee (RNC). It includes correspondence, documents pertaining to official RNC events, official statements from Gabrielson as RNC chairman, a scrapbook of news clippings from his early political career, correspondence, photographs, various material documenting the operations of the RNC such as state elections and regional conferences. The largest part of the collection consists of files related to the 1952 RNC national convention.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Early Political Career, 1925-1944, Undated
Series 2 - Republican National Committee Papers, 1948-1967, Undated
Series 3 - Republican National Committee 1952 Convention, 1948-1956, Undated
Series are arranged alphabetically.
Series - Series 1: Early Political Career, 1948-1956,
Series - Series 2: Republican National Committee Papers, 1948-1956,
Series - Series 3: Republican National Committee 1952 Convention, 1948-1956,
Subject and Genre Headings
Public Servants; Gabrielson, Guy George, 1891-1976; Taft, Robert Alphonso, 1889-1953; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944; Republican National Committee (U.S.); Republican National Committee (U.S.)--Congresses; Republican Party (Essex County, N.J.); Republican Party (N.J.); Republican National Convention; Politicians--Washington (D.C.); Campaign literature--United States; Presidents--United States--Election--1940; Presidents--United States--Election--1952; Washington (D.C.)--Politics and government; Essex County (N.J.); Chicago (Ill.); Clippings; Correspondence; Photographs; Speeches; Brochures; Minutes; Memorabilia; Agendas (administrative records); Files by subject; Digital Files
Container List
- Early Political Career, 1925-1944; nam_apap248-1
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains a scrapbook of news clippings from Guy George Gabrielsons early political career in New Jersey state government (1925-1940), materials related to his role as the chairman of the New Jersey Campaign Committee for U.S. presidential candidate Wendell Willkie, additional news clippings related to New Jersey Republican political activities, rules and resolutions of the Committee, and correspondence with private citizens and various New Jersey politicians. Topics include finances, elections and organizations.
  - Farmers National Bank, Iowa Church Dedication, 1928; 1930; 1934; nam_apap248-1_1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gabrielson Speeches, 1940; Undated; nam_apap248-1_2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New Jersey Political Correspondence, 1927-1929; nam_apap248-1_3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - N.J. State Republican Campaign Committee, 1940; nam_apap248-1_4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - News Clippings- Willkie Campaign, 1940; Undated; nam_apap248-1_5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New Jersey Italian American Newspaper Willkie Endorsement, 1940; nam_apap248-1_6 (Flat-file 1)
  - Photos of Gabrielson, 1943; Undated; nam_apap248-1_7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photos of Wendell Willkie's Presidential Campaign, 1940; nam_apap248-1_8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Political Correspondence, 1940-1944; nam_apap248-1_9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1925-1929; 1939-1940; nam_apap248-1_10 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
- Republican National Committee Papers, 1948-1967; nam_apap248-2
  This series includes addresses and statements from Guy George Gabrielson as Republican National Committee Chairman, committee reports, itineraries, committee meeting minutes, campaign materials, regional conference proceedings, official news releases, and printed pamphlets. Topics include the investigation into Gabrielsons ties to Carthage Hydrocol, Inc., state elections, member organizations, such as the Young Republicans, finances, and schools of politics.
  - Addresses and Statements by Chairman Gabrielson, 1949; nam_apap248-2_1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Addresses and Statements by Chairman Gabrielson, 1950 January-1950 April; nam_apap248-2_2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Addresses and Statements by Chairman Gabrielson, 1950 May-1950 December; nam_apap248-2_3 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Addresses and Statements by Chairman Gabrielson, 1951; nam_apap248-2_4 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Addresses and Statements by Chairman Gabrielson, 1952 January-1952 June; nam_apap248-2_5 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bennett, John, 1950; nam_apap248-2_6 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Budget- Finances, etc., 1950; 1952; nam_apap248-2_7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Campaign- Hatch Act, Expenses, etc., 1952; nam_apap248-2_8 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Campaign Speech Kit, 1950; nam_apap248-2_9 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Campaign Speech Kit National republican Congressional Committee, 1950; nam_apap248-2_10 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Capitol Hill Club, 1951; 1961; 1962; 1966; Undated; nam_apap248-2_11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chairman Gabrielson, 1950 February; nam_apap248-2_12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chairman Gabrielson- Personal, 1949-1952; nam_apap248-2_13 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Chairman Gabrielson- Carthage Hydrocol, 1950-1951; nam_apap248-2_14 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chairman Gabrielson- Carthage Hydrocol Senate Hearing, 1951; nam_apap248-2_15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chairman Gabrielson Miscellaneous, Undated; nam_apap248-2_16 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Chairman Pfeiffer- New York Republican State Committee, 1951; nam_apap248-2_17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - The Chairman's Letter, 1951; nam_apap248-2_18 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Condolences, 1950-1951; nam_apap248-2_19 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Eastern Regional Conference Mayflower Hotel, Washington, D.C, 1951 October 01; nam_apap248-2_20 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Eastern Regional Republican Conference Planning, 1951 October; nam_apap248-2_21 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Editorial Digest", 1950; nam_apap248-2_22 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Ethnic Origin Division- RNC, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-2_23 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Executive Committee Chicago, 1950 May; nam_apap248-2_24 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Meeting and Eastern Seaboard Regional Conference Atlantic City, N.J, 1950 June 23; nam_apap248-2_25 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Meeting and Western Regional Conference Salt Lake City, 1950 July 31-1950 August 01; nam_apap248-2_26 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee meeting of the RNC and Eastern Regional Conference Mayflower Hotel, D.C, 1951 October 01; nam_apap248-2_27 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting RNC Salt Lake City, 1950 July-1950 August; nam_apap248-2_28 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Meeting Washington, D.C, 1950 December 08; nam_apap248-2_29 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Itineraries, 1949-1951; nam_apap248-2_30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters Re. Campaign and Election, 1950; nam_apap248-2_31 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mailing Lists, 1950; nam_apap248-2_32 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Material for Letters and Speeches, 1949; Undated; nam_apap248-2_33 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Meeting- Budget and Finance Committee, 1948-1950; nam_apap248-2_34 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Meeting- Exec. Committee-RNC Chicago, 1950 May; nam_apap248-2_35 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Meeting- Exec. Committee-RNC Washington D.C., 1950 December; nam_apap248-2_36 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Member Lists of State Central Committees, 1951; nam_apap248-2_37 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Minutes- RNC Washington, D.C, 1951 January; nam_apap248-2_38 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Missouri Republican Club Certificate, 1949; nam_apap248-2_39 (Oversized 2, Folder 1)
  - Mock Conventions, 1952; Undated; nam_apap248-2_40 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - National Committee Meeting Chicago, 1950 September 15-1950 September 16; nam_apap248-2_41 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - National Committee Meeting Chicago, 1951 January; nam_apap248-2_42 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Federation of Women's Republican Clubs, 1949-1955; nam_apap248-2_43 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - "On the Political Front", 1950-1952; nam_apap248-2_44 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Pro- America, 1942-1943; 1951; nam_apap248-2_45 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Re- Christmas Cards, 1950-1951; nam_apap248-2_46 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Regional Conferences Eastern Seaboard, 1950; nam_apap248-2_47 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Regional Meetings, 1960-1961; nam_apap248-2_48 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Releases, Biogs, etc., 1949-1952; nam_apap248-2_49 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Report from George Murphy and Associates Re Go- Party, 1962; nam_apap248-2_50 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Report of the Chairman of the Finance Committee, 1950; nam_apap248-2_51 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Republican Farm Conference- Sioux City, 1949-1950; nam_apap248-2_52 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - RNC, 1951; nam_apap248-2_53 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - RNC, 1952; nam_apap248-2_54 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - RNC Committee Meetings, 1950; nam_apap248-2_55 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - RNC Lists of Officers, Exec. Committee and Members, 1949-1952; nam_apap248-2_56 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - RNC Meeting and Midwestern and Western National Conference Tulsa, 1951; nam_apap248-2_57 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - RNC Meeting and Midwestern and Western National Conference Tulsa, Okla. Gen. Info, 1951 May 11-1951 May 12; nam_apap248-2_58 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - RNC Meeting and Report of Finance Committee San Francisco, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-2_59 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - RNC Meeting Chicago, 1952; Undated; nam_apap248-2_60 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - RNC Meeting- Executive Session Washington, D.C., 1951 October; nam_apap248-2_61 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - RNC Meeting Executive Session Washington, D.C, 1951 January; nam_apap248-2_62 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - RNC Meeting Minutes, 1950-1951; nam_apap248-2_63 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - RNC Meeting San Francisco, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-2_64 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - RNC Meeting San Francisco, 1952 January; nam_apap248-2_65 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - RNC Meeting- Tulsa, Oklahoma, 1951 May; nam_apap248-2_66 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - RNC Meeting Washington, D.C., 1949-1950; nam_apap248-2_67 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - RNC Meeting Washington, D.C., 1950; nam_apap248-2_68 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - RNC Meeting Washington, D.C., 1951; nam_apap248-2_69 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - RNC National Farm Conference Sioux City, 1949 September 23; nam_apap248-2_70 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - RNC National Farm Conference Sioux City, 1949 September 24; nam_apap248-2_71 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - RNC News Releases and Publications, 1950-1951; Undated; nam_apap248-2_72 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - RNC Publications- Campaign/Organizations Strategy, 1951; Undated; nam_apap248-2_73 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - RNC Publications- History and Background, 1951-1952; 1967; nam_apap248-2_74 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - RNC Regional Conferences, 1950-1951; nam_apap248-2_75 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - RNC Secretary Mrs. Charles P. Howard, 1949-1952; nam_apap248-2_76 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - RNC Secretary- Mrs. Knowles, 1949; nam_apap248-2_77 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - School of Politics, 1950; 1950-1952; Undated; nam_apap248-2_78 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Speakers Bureau- Radio/TV, 1950; 1954; Undated; nam_apap248-2_79 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - State Elections, 1948-1950; nam_apap248-2_80 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Truman Research, 1951; nam_apap248-2_81 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Women's Division, 1950-1952; nam_apap248-2_82 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Women's Federation, 1950; Undated; nam_apap248-2_83 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Young Republicans, 1950-1952; nam_apap248-2_84 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Republican National Committee 1952 Convention, 1948-1956; nam_apap248-3; 1 Digital Files
  The bulk of this series is a by-product of the exhaustive planning for the 1952 Republican National Convention that nominated General Dwight D. Eisenhower for president. It includes committee reports, correspondence with local businesses, candidate information, the official convention program and campaign materials. Topics include finance, hotels/housing, chaplains, doorkeepers and preparatory actions by various state committees.
  - Applications- General, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Assignments, 1952; nam_apap248-3_2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Assistant Chairman, 1952; nam_apap248-3_3 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Background Information, 1948; Undated; nam_apap248-3_4 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - California, 1951; nam_apap248-3_5 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Campaign, 1952; Undated; nam_apap248-3_6 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Campaign Material, 1950-1952; Undated; nam_apap248-3_7 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Candidate Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1951-1952; 1956; nam_apap248-3_8 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Candidate Macarthur, Douglas, 1952; nam_apap248-3_9 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Candidate Stassen, Harold, E., 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_10 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Candidate Taft, Robert A., 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_11 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Candidate Warren, Earl, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_12 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Chairman, Undated; nam_apap248-3_13 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Chairman- Finance, 1950-1951; Undated; nam_apap248-3_14 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Chaplains, 1952; Undated; nam_apap248-3_15 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Chicago Convention Bldg. and International Amphitheatre, 1952; nam_apap248-3_16 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Chicago Site Solicitation, Undated; nam_apap248-3_17 (Box 4, Folder 24-25)
  - Convent Information/Official Program, 1952; Undated; nam_apap248-3_18 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Committee on Arrangements, 1950-1952; nam_apap248-3_19 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Committee on Arrangements, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_20 (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Committee on Arrangements, 1952; nam_apap248-3_21 (Box 4, Folder 30-34)
  - Committee on Arrangements- Mooberg, Henry E., 1952; nam_apap248-3_22 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Committee on Arrangements- Report of Housing Subcommittee, 1953; Undated; nam_apap248-3_23 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Committee on Arrangements San Francisco, 1952 January; nam_apap248-3_24 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Committee on Arrangements San Francisco Executive Session, 1952 January; nam_apap248-3_25 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Committee on Arrangements Treasurer, 1952; nam_apap248-3_26 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Committee on Call, 1950-1952; nam_apap248-3_27 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Committee on Call, 1950-1952; nam_apap248-3_28 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Contests, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_29 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Resolutions (Platform), 1952; nam_apap248-3_30 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Rules, 1948; 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_31 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Site, 1951; nam_apap248-3_32 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Site, 1951-1952; Undated; nam_apap248-3_33 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Site- Meetings, 1951; nam_apap248-3_34 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Committee Reports, Undated; nam_apap248-3_35 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Committees and Subcommittees, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_36 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Contest- Florida, 1952; nam_apap248-3_37 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Contest- Georgia, 1952; nam_apap248-3_38 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Contest- Louisiana, 1952; nam_apap248-3_39 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Contests, 1952; nam_apap248-3_40 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Contracts, 1951; nam_apap248-3_41 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Convention Assignments, 1952; nam_apap248-3_42 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Convention Balloons, Undated; nam_apap248-3_43 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Convention Prayers, Undated; nam_apap248-3_44 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Credentials Committee, 1952; nam_apap248-3_45 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Delegates, 1951-1952; Undated; nam_apap248-3_46 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Doorkeepers, 1952; Undated; nam_apap248-3_47 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Finance, 1951; nam_apap248-3_48 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Florida, 1951; nam_apap248-3_49 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Form Letters, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_50 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Hotels, 1952; nam_apap248-3_51 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Housing, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_52 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Invitation to Hold 1952 Convention in Philadelphia, Shaped Like a Key, ca. 1950; nam_apap248-3_53 (Oversized 2, Folder 2)
  - Invitation to Hold 1956 Convention in San Francisco, Including Magazine and Brochures, 1953; nam_apap248-3_54 (Flat-file 1)
  - Invocations, Undated; nam_apap248-3_55 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_56 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Mississippi, 1951; nam_apap248-3_57 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Missouri, 1951; nam_apap248-3_58 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - New York, 1951; nam_apap248-3_59 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Oklahoma, 1951; nam_apap248-3_60 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Parliamentarians, 1952; nam_apap248-3_61 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Permanent Chairman, 1952; nam_apap248-3_62 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Proxies, 1952; nam_apap248-3_63 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Reapportionment- General, 1951; nam_apap248-3_64 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Republican National Committee- Nominations, 1952; nam_apap248-3_65 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Resolutions, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_66 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Sergeant-at-Arms, 1952; Undated; nam_apap248-3_67 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Site Committee- Correspondence, 1951; nam_apap248-3_68 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Subcommittee- Television and Motion Pictures, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_69 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Subcommittee- Tickets, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_70 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Subcommittee- Music and Decorations, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_71 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Subcommittee on Badges, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_72 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Subcommittee or Housing- General, 1952; nam_apap248-3_73 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Subcommittee on Transportation and Parking, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_74 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Subcommittee- Program and Concessions, 1951-1952; Undated; nam_apap248-3_75 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Subcommittee- Radio and Press- General, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_76 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Temporary Chairman, 1952; nam_apap248-3_77 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Tickets, 1951-1952; nam_apap248-3_78 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Tickets, 1952; nam_apap248-3_79 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Washington, 1951; nam_apap248-3_80 (Box 5, Folder 51)